Finding Aid for Dental Research Institute (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dental Research Institute (University of Michigan) records 1965-1989
University of Michigan. Dental Research Institute.
4.5 linear feet
9542 Bimu 2
The records of the University of Michigan Dental Research Institute document the administration, development, funding, and research activities of the Institute from its inception in 1965, through the termination of National Institute of Dental Research funding in 1989.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received from the Dental Research Institute in 1991 and 1996. (Donor Number 7891 )
No further additions to the records expected.
The collection is open for research.
The Dental Research Institute at the University of Michigan was approved by the Board of Regents on October 21, 1966. The Institute was established through the collaboration of the School of Dentistry, the Medical School, the School of Public Health, and the National Institutes of Health (NIH). The National Institute of Dental Research affiliate of the NIH provided funding through a series of grants. One of five such institutes in the country, the Dental Research Institute at the University of Michigan was devoted to research, education, and the dissemination of research findings through teaching, publication, and clinical practice. By collaborating with university scientists in allied fields, the Institute utilized an interdisciplinary approach to address important areas of dental health care, and expand the knowledge of oral biology and pathology while also training future dental health care providers.
The multi-disciplinary thrust of the program was directed toward three major research areas: Periodontal Diseases and Caries, Viral Diseases of the Oral Cavity, and Growth and Function of Masticatory Apparatus. Basic science research was conducted in several laboratory components, including: bacteriology, biochemistry, bioengineering, biometrics, cell biology, experimental pathology, genetics, immunology, histology, molecular biology, neurophysiology, pharmacology, and virology.
The Institute was initiated on June 1, 1967, with the arrival of Dominic Dziewiatkowski as director. He began the process of recruiting research scientists for the Institute. Recruitment was hampered by the lack of adequate research facilities, a situation that was not remedied until 1970 when the research tower at the Dental Building was completed. He also established the Policy, Executive, and Scientific Advisory committees to aid the review of research priorities and administration of the Institute.
Dziewiatkowski resigned and was succeeded by Harold Loe in 1972. By that time Institute staff consisted of 40 researchers and an equal number of supporting staff members. During Loe's tenure the symposium program begun by his predecessor to disseminate research results was expanded, resulting in several conferences and publications.
In 1976, Dr. James Avery was appointed director of the Institute. Avery had previously served as acting director in 1972 and in 1975. Among his key contributions was the development of the Associate Member Program, a multi-disciplinary scientific outreach program that involved scientists outside of the Dental Research Institute in research relating the Institute's objectives.
On February 28, 1989, after 22 years, National Institute of Dental Research funding ended. A no-cost time extension carried support through February 28, 1990. Although the major source of funding ended, many of the collaboratory efforts and key research projects managed to continue through alternative funding.
Directors of the Dental research Institute
1967-1972 Dr. Dominic Dziewiatkowski
1972-1975 Dr. Harold Loe
1976-1989 Dr. James K. Avery
The records of the University of Michigan Dental Research Institute document the administration, development, funding, and research activities of the Institute from its inception in 1965, through the termination of National Institute of Dental Research funding in 1989. The Institute records are organized into five records series: Grant Applications, Committee Records, Topical Files, Associate Member Program, and Printed Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dental Research Institute.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; National Institute of Dental Research (U.S.); Dentistry--Research.; Dentistry--Research--Michigan.
- Grant Applications
  The Applications series dates from 1965 to 1989 and consists of grant applications, and material relating to the preparation of grants, including research outlines, budgets, award notices, and correspondence with the granting agency. The application records include five-year grants which provided the majority of the funding, and several competing and non-competing renewal grant applications. The annual reports prepared as part of the grant process are to be found in the Printed Materials series which is described at the end of this section.
  - Five Year Grant Applications
    - 1972-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - (Renewal) Applications, Awards, Budgets
    - 1967-1971, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1971-1973, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1973-1977, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1977-1983, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - 19th Year 1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 20th Year 1986 (Box 2)
    - 21st Year 1987 (Box 2)
    - Final Year 1988 (Box 2)
- Committee Records
  Committee Records include the files of committees that reviewed the scientific research and administered the Institute. These include the Policy Committee, 1973-1986, and the Scientific Advisory Committee, 1967-1986. Policy Committee records mainly focus on space and budget allocations. Scientific Advisory Committee records relate to the evaluation of the Institute's scientific program. A third committee, the Executive Committee, was responsible for the operation of the Institute and related policy matters. Also include here are search committee files from director searches.
  - Director Search Committee
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee
    - Minutes 1967-1972 (Box 2)
  - Policy Committee
    - 1968-1983, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
  - Scientific Advisory Committee
    - 1967-1986, 22 folders (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files is an alphabetically arranged series. It contains material from the Institute including correspondence, research proposals, symposiums, and site visits. Site visits consists of background files as well as reports made by the visiting committees during periodically required site visits.
  - Aims, Purpose and Guidelines 1965-1983 (Box 3)
  - Annual Report Data and Summaries 1978-1988 (Box 3)
  - Avery, James 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Dental Research Building 1978 (Box 3)
  - Doyle, Barbara 1972 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence 1966-1970 (Box 3)
  - Program Reviews 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Research Proposals 1968-1981 (Box 3)
  - St. Joseph Hospital (space) 1978 (Box 3)
  - Site Visits
    - 1965-1984, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Symposiums 1970-1987 (Box 3)
- Associate Member Program
  The Associate Member Program series includes administrative records of the program as well as research proposals and reports from twenty-three projects funded under the program from its inception in 1978 through 1988. The records highlight the multi-disciplinary aspect of this program which was supported in part by university funds through the Office of Vice President for Research.
  - General 1978-1988 (Box 3)
  - Research Projects 1978-1988, 22 folders (Box 3)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series includes annual reports, brochures, and newsletters of the Dental Research Institute, and proceedings from the Institute and School of Dentistry co-sponsored symposium program. There is a complete run of annual and semi-annual reports from 1967-1989 arranged chronologically. This record group also contains an almost complete run, 1977-1989, of the newsletter Dental Research Institute Bulletin. Arranged chronologically, the symposium proceedings were published to disseminate research results from September 1970 to March 1987. They include the symposium on Herpes, Hepatitis, and AIDS: Current Concerns of the Health Practitioner which was held in November 1983.
  - Unit Publications
    - Abstracts
      - Dental Research Institute Abstracts, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports
      - Semi-Annual Report
        - June-November 1967 (Box 4)
        - December 1967-November 1968 (Box 4)
      - Report of the Director
        - October 1969 (Box 4)
        - December 1969 (Box 4)
      - Annual Summary Report, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
      - Application Progress Report, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
      - Annual Report of the Director, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Annual Report, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Summary Report, 1967-1971, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Summary Report, 1971-1972, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Annual Report, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Annual Summary Progress Report
        - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Annual Report, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Annual Progress Report, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
      - Annual Report, 1977-1989, 13 folders (Box 4)
    - Brochures Undated (Box 5)
    - Newsletters
      - Dental Research Institute Bulletin, 1977-1989 vol. 1-8, 7 folders (Box 5)
      - Newsletter, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Proceedings
      - Research Perspectives in Dentistry, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Dental Plaque: Interfaces, 1973 (Box 5)
      - Oral and Perioral Ulcerations: Cause and Control, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Occlusion: Research In Form and Function, 1975 (Box 5)
      - The Scientific Basis for Evaluation of Periodontal Therapy, 1976 (Box 5)
      - Incipient Caries of Enamel, 1977 (Box 5)
      - Diet, Nutrition, and Dental Caries, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Trends in the Prevention and Treatment of Periodontal Disease, 1981 (Box 5)
      - Dental Pulp: Reactions to Restorative Materials in the Presence or Absence of Infection, 1982 (Box 5)
      - Herpes, Hepatitis and AIDS: Current Concerns of the Health Practitioner, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Hypersensitive Dentin: Origin and Management, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Insights Into Dentofacial Pain: Overview, Diagnosis and Treatment, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Salvary Glands and their Secretion, 1972 (Box 5)